<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
	<head>
		<meta xml:lang="fr" name="keywords"
			content="article,enregistrement,ogg,rendu,carton,orgue" />
		<meta xml:lang="en" name="keywords"
			content="article,recording,ogg,book,organ" />
		<link href="../site.css" type="text/css" media="screen"
			rel="StyleSheet" />
		<title xml:lang="fr">
			Enregistrement d'un rendu de carton dans un fichier OGG
			(comme MP3)
		</title>
		<title xml:lang="en">
			Recording the aprint book sound rendering in a mp3 like file
			format (OGG)
		</title>
	</head>
	<body>
		<a href="articles.html">
			<span xml:lang="fr">[Retour]</span>
			<span xml:lang="en">[Back]</span>
		</a>
		<br />
		<h1 xml:lang="fr">
			Enregistrer le rendu sonore d'APrint dans un fichier OGG
			(comme les fichiers MP3)
		</h1>
		<h1 xml:lang="en">
			Recording the aprint book sound rendering in a mp3 like file
			format (OGG)
		</h1>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			APrint has a functionnality to record the rendering of a
			midi file, using the instruments defined with APrint in an
			audio file format that can be shared without giving the Midi
			file. Thoses files could also be used in MP3 players, ipods
			..
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			APrint a une fonctionnalité permettant d'enregistrer le
			rendu APrint d'un fichier midi dans un format audio pouvant
			etre utilisé par ailleurs. Cela permet également de pouvoir
			partager un morceau avec d'autres utilisateurs sans envoyer
			le fichier midi, et plus simple d'utilisation qu'un logiciel
			midi.
		</p>

		<h2 xml:lang="fr">Format de fichier OGG</h2>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Le format OGG est un format de fichier audio utilisant une
			méthode de compression similaire à MP3, mais ayant une plus
			grande qualité. Ce format est généralement préféré au MP3
			car il est libre de droit. La plupart des logiciels
			permettant d'écouter des fichiers MP3 sont maintenant
			capable de lire nativement ce type de fichiers. Si le
			logiciel que vous utilisez ne sait pas lire le format OGG,
			vous pouvez visiter la page wikipedia sur le sujet, celle ci
			vous redirigera vers les plugins fournissant cette
			possibilité pour votre logiciel d'écoute.
			<a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogg">
				Page Wikipedia sur le Format OGG
			</a>
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			Ogg is a free, open standard container format maintained by
			the Xiph.Org Foundation. The creators of the Ogg format
			claim that it is unrestricted by software patents and is
			designed to provide for efficient streaming and manipulation
			of high quality digital multimedia.
			<br />

			The name ‘Ogg’ refers to the file format which can multiplex
			a number of separate independent free and open source codecs
			for audio, video, text (such as subtitles), and metadata.
			<br />

			In the Ogg multimedia framework, Theora provides a lossy
			video layer, while the music-oriented Vorbis codec most
			commonly acts as the audio layer. The human speech
			compression codec Speex, lossless audio compression codec
			FLAC, and OggPCM may also act as audio layers.
			<br />

			The term ‘Ogg’ is commonly used to refer to audio file
			format Ogg Vorbis, that is, Vorbis-encoded audio in the Ogg
			container. Previously, the .ogg file extension was used for
			any content distributed within Ogg, but as of 2007, the
			Xiph.Org Foundation requests that .ogg be used only for
			Vorbis due to backward compatibility concerns. The Xiph.Org
			Foundation decided to create a new set of file extensions
			and media types to describe different types of content such
			as .oga for audio only files, .ogv for video with or without
			sound (including Theora), and .ogx for applications.
			<br />

			The current version of the Xiph.Org Foundation's reference
			implementation, released on June 23, 2009, is libogg 1.1.4.
			Another version, libogg2, has been in development, but is
			awaiting a rewrite as of 2008[4]. Both software libraries
			are free software, released under the new BSD license. Ogg
			reference implementation was separated from Vorbis on
			September 2, 2000.
			<br />

			Because the format is free, and its reference implementation
			is non-copylefted, Ogg's various codecs have been
			incorporated into a number of different free and proprietary
			media players, both commercial and non-commercial, as well
			as portable media players and GPS receivers from different
			manufacturers.
			<br />

			Le format OGG est un format de fichier audio utilisant une
			méthode de compression similaire à MP3, mais ayant une plus
			grande qualité. Ce format est généralement préféré au MP3
			car il est libre de droit. La plupart des logiciels
			permettant d'écouter des fichiers MP3 sont maintenant
			capable de lire nativement ce type de fichiers.
			<br />


		</p>



		<h2 xml:lang="fr">Comment enregistrer le fichier</h2>
		<h2 xml:lang="en">How to create the OGG File</h2>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Après avoir sélectionner un fichier midi, puis un
			instrument, la page de présentation du carton vous propose
			un bouton permettant de faire cela
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="en">
			Once you have selected a midi file, an instrument and
			whatching the book view, a top button permit to create the
			OGG File.
		</p>

		<img xml:lang="en" src="../common/recording-1.png"
			title="This button permit to record the file as an audio OGG file"
			alt="This button permit to record the file as an audio OGG file" />

		<img xml:lang="fr" src="../common/recording-1.png"
			title="Ce bouton permet de creer le fichier audio OGG du rendu du carton"
			alt="Ce bouton permet de creer le fichier audio OGG du rendu du carton" />


		<br />

		<p xml:lang="en">
			This function will ask for a file name to save. The
			processing can take a couple of seconds.
		</p>

		<p xml:lang="fr">
			une fois sélectionné, le logiciel demandera alors un nom et
			un emplacement de fichier. Le temps de traitement de la
			fonction peut prendre quelques secondes.
		</p>



		<script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js"
			type="text/javascript">
		</script>
		<script type="text/javascript">
			_uacct = "UA-1958863-2"; urchinTracker();
		</script>
	</body>
</page>
